[music]
>> In February 2012, pro skier Elyse
Saugstad was carving through the slopes
of the Cascade Mountains when a crack
formed in the snowpack above her. Before
she was fully engulfed by a 5,000 ton
wall of snow, Elyse heard, "Avalanche!"
just in time to react with a life-saving
maneuver.
So, how could she survive this crushing
snow search? [music]
Avalanches are the rapid descent of
snow, ice, rock, or a combination of
these down a slope. They can be
destructive natural disasters and
personal tragedies. In the United States
alone, avalanches kill an average of 27
people [music]
annually.
These Alpine nightmares don't just
awaken out of nowhere. They need three
specific conditions.
First, the [music] mountain needs to
have the right slope.
Typically between 30° and 45°. [music]
This is shallow enough to allow snow to
build up on the slope, yet steep enough
to provide enough potential energy for
movement. Second, [music]
they typically need a layer of sturdy
snow deposited over a weak or unstable
layer, or what's sometimes called
something over nothing.
Take the Cascade Mountain avalanche
where recent heavy storms deposited a
nearly 1 m deep slab of fresh snow.
Below this sat [music] a thin layer of
surface hoar. These are delicate
feathery ice crystals that form when
water vapor in the air rapidly freezes
on the surface of snow, almost like dew
in the wintertime.
Finally, avalanches need a trigger,
something to collapse [music] the weak
layer and put the snow in motion. A
trigger can be natural, such as heavy
snowfall, strong winds, rainfall, or
even other avalanches.
Or they can be human caused, like the
surface impact of skiers or
snowmobilers.
Since fractures can propagate quickly
through the snowpack, triggers can
originate hundreds of meters away,
upstream, downstream, or even adjacent
to the avalanche's path.
Once in motion, how quickly an avalanche
moves depends on the slope's steepness,
its exposure or vegetation cover,
terrain roughness, and the type and
amount of snow involved.
For example, dry, light, and loosely
[music] bonded snow tends to travel
fast, forming a powder cloud as it
moves.
In contrast, wet snow avalanches, caused
by water moving through the snowpack,
travel more slowly but are much denser
[music] and can be particularly
destructive. Larger avalanches can
travel more than 160 km [music] per
hour, breaking trees, destroying
buildings, and burying roadways.
In 1970, one particularly massive
avalanche, consisting of 50 to 100
million cubic meters of glacial ice,
snow, mud, and rock reached speeds of
over 300 km per hour. This avalanche
proved to be the deadliest in history,
engulfing an entire Peruvian town and
killing 18,000 [music] people.
Avalanches aren't always this large, but
even smaller ones can be dangerous for
anyone caught in their path. As snow
rushes downhill, it can behave like both
a solid and a liquid, making its
movement difficult to predict. At the
fastest moving front, surface snow moves
faster than the snow beneath, pulling
victims deep into the snowpack and
scattering [music] them across wide
areas, making rescue difficult.
Once an avalanche slows, the snow loses
its fluid-like properties and compacts,
leaving victims immobilized and unable
to escape on their own.
For these reasons, the best way to
survive an avalanche is to avoid one
altogether.
Thankfully, at most ski resorts, parks,
and even highways,
avalanche workers mitigate risk by
continuously monitoring the weather,
stability of the snowpack, and human
activity. If a threat is detected,
they'll close terrain and may even
intentionally trigger a controlled
avalanche with explosives or artillery.
However, there are regions where
avalanche risk [music] is not actively
mitigated, known as the backcountry.
Here, you are responsible for managing
your own risk. Local avalanche centers
provide avalanche forecasts, and anyone
entering the backcountry should
understand them, be properly trained,
and carry essential [music]
rescue gear. And ultimately, in
high-hazard terrain, there's no way to
completely eliminate risk. The group at
the Cascade Mountains consisted of
highly experienced skiers, [music] yet
the area was very exposed, and following
a large storm, the avalanche danger
forecast was elevated. In the end, three
skiers lost their lives, but not at
least as she was able to deploy an
inflatable airbag. These devices are
imperfect and a last line of defense,
yet can keep a victim closer to the
surface, improving their chance of
rescue should disaster strike.
Ready to keep learning? Watch these
videos to either challenge what you
think you know, or learn more about what
you don't. Subscribe and stay curious.
>> [music]